(悟)＜18年前の３月１日＞
March 1st, 18 years ago.
As usual, Hinazuki was standing
alone in this park.
＜いつものように 雛月は一人で
この公園に立っていた＞
I think it was a little before six.
＜時間は ６時少し前だったか＞
At the time,
I was on my way to the hideout.
＜あのとき
俺は アジトへ向かった＞
I went looking for my missing gloves.
＜なくした手袋を
取りに行ったはずだ＞
I don't remember
if the gloves were actually there.
＜手袋があったかどうかは
覚えていない＞
After leaving the hideout,
I looked towards the bank
＜アジトから出て土手に目をやると
川の方を向いて座る ユウキさんが見えた＞
and saw Yuuki sitting there,
facing the river.
After that, when I cut back
through the park,
＜その後 ほぼ最短距離で
公園に戻って 通り過ぎたとき➡
Hinazuki was gone.
雛月の姿は もう
そこにはなかった＞
February 24th
All right, all eyes on the blackboard.
(八代)はい 黒板に注目｡
Kayo Hinazuki is going to be the first victim
in a series of kidnappings and murders,
雛月加代が連続誘拐殺人事件
最初の被害者になるまであと１週間
a week from now.
MARCH
X-day.
《Ｘデー… ３月１日を
無事に乗り切って➡
Safely getting through March 1st
and spending the next day
with Hinazuki at my birthday party...
翌日の誕生会を 雛月と過ごす》
That would definitely change the future.
《それこそが
未来を変えることになる》
I'll make sure
those crimes never happen.
《事件そのものを
なくしてやる！》
♬～
ERASED
February 25th 1988
Morning, Satoru.
(佐知子)おはよう 悟｡
Morning.
(悟)おはよう｡
朝ご飯 もう少し待ってね｡
Breakfast will be ready in a few.
Yea...
ふぁーい…｡
Thank you for this meal.
いただきます｡
Hey, Mom...
あのさ お母さん｡
ん？
I want to go out next Saturday.
今度の土曜日
ちょっと出掛けたいんだけど｡
On a date?
デート？
そっ そんなんじゃないけど…｡
N-Not like that!
I thought we'd all go
to the Science Center.
みんなで
科学センター行こうと思って｡
Oh. Too bad.
何だ｡ デートなら
お小遣いあげるのにさ｡
If it were a date,
I'd give you money for it.
Seriously?
《マジか!?》
It really is a date, isn't it?
ホントは デートだべ？
うん｡
Yeah.
You should bring her here.
うちにも連れてくればいいべさ｡
鍋でも食べるベ｡
We'll have hot pot or something.
Hinazuki will be here
for the birthday party.
雛月なら 誕生日会のとき来るよ｡
Oh. Hinazuki, from the fifth block.
ああ ５街区の雛月さんか｡
She's already asking me
leading questions.
《まんまと
誘導尋問されちまってる》
Just be careful when you go out.
気を付けて行ってきなよ｡
Thank you.
ありがとう｡
さっ 早く食べちゃいな｡
Now hurry up and eat your breakfast.
Right!
うん｡
Ice Hockey Club
1988 National Champions
Rise.
(児童)起立｡ 礼｡
(児童たち)さようならー｡
Manners.
Goodbye!
"Liveman" is starting soon! Isn't it cool?
今度 始まる『ライブマン』
カッコ良くね？
Yeah!
(児童)カッコイイ！
(児童)ファルコンって何？
What's a "falcon"?
A hunting bird!
(児童)ハヤブサだよ！
(児童)物知り！
You know a lot!
Saturday...
《土曜日 雛月を家から…》
I'm going to take Hinazuki away
from her house or,
more precisely, her mother's abuse.
《いや あの母親の暴力から
引き剥がすんだ》
- Sensei!
(児童たち)先生｡ 先生｡
(八代)何だい？
What is it?
I don't get this, so explain it to me.
ここ分かんないから 教えて｡
ん？ どれどれ？
Let's see...
(美里)チッ｡
みんな色ボケてて 腹立つ｡
It ticks me off
how they're all so flirty with him.
You know everything, Sensei!
Until recently,
お前だって 最近まで
あいつらの中の一人だったろ｡
you were the same way, weren't you?
Don't be stubborn.
意地張ってないで
お前も行けばいいじゃん｡
You can go up there, too, y'know.
What's that, "y'know"?
｢じゃん｣って何？
カッコつけてんの？
Are you trying to sound cool?
Crap.
《しまった…》
Sensei thinks I'm a thief.
(美里)先生は 私のこと
泥棒だって思ってるべさ｡➡
And so do you.
あんただってそうだべ｡
もういいんだ｡
Never mind.
Hey, you guys. I have an idea.
ねえ みんな｡提案があるんだけど｡
(オサム)何？ 悟｡
What is it, Satoru?
Um...
あの… 土曜日 みんなで科学センター行かない？
雛月も一緒なんだけど｡
Why don't we all go
to the Science Center on Saturday?
I'm gonna ask Hinazuki, too.
That's a great!
あっ それ いっ…！
Sorry, Satoru.
(ケンヤ)ごめん 悟｡
俺 その日 外せない用事がある｡
I have something to do that day
and I can't get out of it.
O-Oh...
え？ そ… そう｡
Sorry, Satoru.
(カズ)すまん 悟｡
俺も大事な用があって行けねえわ｡
I got somethin' important
to do, so I can't go either.
T-That's right.
そっ そうそう｡ 行きたいけど
俺も用事があってさ｡
I wanna go, but I've got
something to do, too.
M-Me too.
(ヒロミ)ぼっ 僕も…｡
そう…｡
Oh...
It's better for just you and Hinazuki to go!
(カズ)雛月と一緒なら
２人の方がいいべや｡
See you!
(オサム)したっけ！
Fujinuma...
(雛月)藤沼｡ 何かあった？
Did something happen?
Uh, no...
あっ いや…｡
I told them I couldn't play on Saturday
because I have a date with you.
土曜日は 雛月とデートだから
遊べないって伝えた｡
Should I say that?
《…とでも言うか？》
I did say that...
《声に出てた》
But...
でも 土曜日は早く帰ってこいって
お母さんが…｡
my mother told me to get home
early on Saturday.
There's a place I wanna take you.
連れていきたい所があるんだ｡
I'll try talking to her.
俺が話してみるからさ｡
Kenya...
≪(八代)ケンヤ！
Could you stop by the staff room?
ちょっと
職員室 寄ってくれないか？
Forget it.
(雛月の母)駄目よ｡
子供が２人で出掛けるなんて｡
I don't believe in two children
going out somewhere together.
It wouldn't just be to play!
ただ 遊びに行くんじゃなくて
勉強しに行くんです！
It's a learning experience, too.
You can learn at home.
(雛月の母)勉強は
家で できるでしょ？
Kayo helps me at home on Saturdays.
(雛月の母)土曜日は 加代が
うちの手伝いをする日なの｡
Helps? With what?
手伝い？ 何の？
Helps you blow off steam?
《お前のストレス発散の
手伝いかよ!?》
I'm not obliged to tell you that.
そんなこと
あんたに言う必要ないでしょ｡
Why do you want Hinazuki
to stay home so badly?
そんなに 雛月が出掛けるの
嫌がる理由は何？
I can think of several reasons!
(雛月の母)そんなの
なんぼでも思い付くわ｡➡
For one, you're both children.
あんたたち 子供でしょ｡➡
If something were to happen,
who would take responsibility?!
何か起きたとき
誰が責任 取んのよ!?
She's turning it against me.
《こいつ 開き直ってやがる》
What's with you?
(雛月の母)あんた何なの？
こんな無愛想な子 連れ出して➡
Taking my surly daughter somewhere...
What do you stand to gain?
何の得があんのよ？
When it comes to saving a friend,
there are no gains or losses!
友達を助けるのに 損も得もない！
Saving?
｢助ける｣？
加代を何から助けるって？
Saving Kayo from what?
You think you're a prince
on a white horse?
白馬の王子さま気取り？
《しまった…》
Crap.
I shouldn't have hinted at her abuse.
《ＤＶに関する言い回しは
やっぱり まずかった》
What do you think, Kayo?
あんたは どうなのさ 加代｡➡
You want to go with this kid?
この子と行きたいっての？
Get your minds out of the gutter,
you perverted brats!
色ボケんな！ このガキども！
Mom!
母さん!?
Stop it, Ms. Hinazuki.
やめなさい 雛月さん｡
You don't call children "perverted brats."
子供たちに向かって
｢色ボケ｣はないべさ｡
Ms... Fujinuma...
藤沼… さん｡
This isn't your business.
人のうちの問題でしょ｡
I'd say half of it is.
(佐知子)半分は
うちの問題だべさ｡➡
You see, my son shows motivation
in everything he does.
子供が何事かに やる気を
見せてるんだからさ｡➡
And I want to help him.
こっちが手伝ってあげようよ｡
親なんだから｡
After all, I'm his parent.
I think your household
and mine are similar.
うちと雛月さんちって
似てると思う｡
Why don't you visit for a chat next time?
今度 うち来て 話さない？
Kayo, get inside.
加代 入りな｡
(雛月)うん｡
Okay.
S-Saturday... I'll see you then.
ど… 土曜日 約束だよ｡
Did I butt in?
出しゃばったべか？
No. Thank you.
ううん｡ ありがとう｡
I got off work early.
(佐知子)
仕事 早く上がれたからさ｡➡
It's lucky that I happened to see you two
and followed you here.
たまたま あんたたち見掛けて
つけてみて よかった｡
You followed us?!
えっ！ つけてきてたの!?
じょ… 冗談に決まってるべさ｡➡
I-I'm kidding, of course.
But... well, everything
should be okay for today.
でも まあ 取りあえず
今日は大丈夫っしょ｡➡
That girl was actually
wearing nice clothes.
あの子 意外と
いい服 着てたべさ｡➡
It's because the mother
cares about appearances.
あれは 母親が
外づら 気にしてるからだべね｡
HINAZUKI
Do you know what's going on over there?
雛月んちのこと知ってんの？
No.
(佐知子)いや｡ でも会話とあの母親
見りゃだいたい察しはつくべさ｡
But between our conversation
and seeing the mother,
I can take a guess.
She didn't work for a TV news
department for nothing.
《さすが 元テレビ局 報道部…》
Kayo is a cute girl.
(佐知子)
めんこい子だね 加代ちゃん｡
What am I embarrassed for?
I'm 29 years old!
《何 照れてんだよ 29歳！》
Don't abandon her now.
「佐知子」　途中で投げ出すんじゃないよ｡
「悟」　当然！
Of course not.
February 27th - Saturday
February 27th, Saturday.
＜２月27日 土曜日｡
その日は よく晴れていた＞
It's a clear day.
It seems Hinazuki's mother has refrained
from physical abuse for the past several days.
＜ここ数日 雛月の母親の暴力は
影を潜めているようだ＞
That's my friend.
こいつ 俺の友達！
Are you stupid?
(雛月)バカなの？
I love this place!
大好きなんだよなぁ ここ｡
There's hardly anyone here.
ほとんど 人いないね｡
Isn't it exciting, like we just snuck in?
勝手に入り込んでるみたいで
ドキドキしない？
When I see somebody else, I hide.
俺 人いたら隠れたりしてるよ｡
She didn't say, "Are you stupid?"
《あっ｡
｢バカなの？｣って言わない》
Look at this!
これ のぞいてみなよ！
PLANETARIUM
Wanna see the planetarium?
プラネタリウム見る？
タイミングいいけど｡
It's good timing.
We saw plenty of stars last time.
星は こないだ散々 見たべさ｡
That's true.
そうだね…｡
I'm gonna run to the bathroom.
あっ 俺 ちょっとトイレ｡
Okay. I'll be around here.
(雛月)うん｡ その辺にいる｡
What is this feeling?
《何だろう？ この感じ》
Is it déjà vu?
《デジャビュなのか？》
I often came here,
《よく来てた場所ではあるけど
雛月と来るのは初めて》
but it's my first time with Hinazuki.
Hinazuki...
雛月…｡
《あっ…》
Fujinuma...
(雛月)藤沼｡
今日は誘ってくれて ありがと｡
Thank you for inviting me today.
Did you know I liked this place, too?
私も ここ好きだって知ってたの？
Did I know?
《｢知ってた｣!?
だから ここを!?》
Is that why I chose this place?
Do people who want to make manga...
《漫画 描こうなんて人は…》 漫画 描こうなんて人は…｡
こういう所 来たがるもんなの？ 《こういう所 来たがるもんなの》
Do people who want to make manga...
tend to come to places like this?
I remember this same
conversation from 18 years ago.
《18年前 同じ会話をしたのを
覚えている》
I came here alone then
and ran into Hinazuki by chance.
《１人で来た俺は ここで偶然
雛月に出会っている》
What is it?
(雛月)何？
いっ いや…｡
N-Nothing.
M-Maybe there is a connection.
か… 関係あるかな？
Am I repeating the same time?
《同じ時を繰り返してる？》
I intend to change the future,
《未来を変えるつもりが知らず知らず
同じ時のレールに 乗ってしまっている？》
but I've unwittingly been riding
the same rail of time?
Hinazuki, I'll carry your coat.
雛月 コート持つよ｡
今？
Now?
I can change a lot
through my own behavior.
《俺の行動によって変わったことだってたくさんある》
Believe it.
《信じろ｡ 未来は変えられる》
I can change the future.
Fujinuma...
(雛月)藤沼｡
I'm glad I mustered
the courage and came here.
勇気出して 来てよかった｡
Yeah...
うん！
Satoru!
Hinazuki!
≪(ケンヤ)悟！
≪(オサム)雛月！
Hey there!
おっす｡ (ケンヤ)用事 早く済んだから
来たよ｡
I finished what I had to do early.
Sorry we're late.
(ヒロミ)遅くなって ごめんね｡
There. It's changed.
《ほら｡ 変わった》
Are we in the way?
(ケンヤ)邪魔だったかな？
そんなことないよ！
Of course not!
Right, Hinazuki?
なっ？ 雛月｡
(雛月)うん｡
Right.
Satoru is a gentleman!
(オサム)あっ 悟 紳士的！
(笑い声)
Episode 4
Accomplishment
5th Grade, Class 4
Good morning!
(児童たち)おはよう｡
Morning, Fujinuma.
(雛月)藤沼｡ おはよう｡
M-Morning, Hinazuki.
おお｡ おはよう 雛月｡
That's a relief.
《よかった｡
月曜日だけど 遅刻しなかった》
It's Monday, but she's not late.
You're pretty.
顔 奇麗だな｡
I actually said that...
《声に出てた…》
D-Did you just hear that?!
February 29th
(児童)きっ 聞いた？ 今の！
(カズ)すげえ！
- Oh my God!
- Satoru's got guts!
Are they gonna get married?!
(ヒロミ)悟君 大胆！
(児童)結婚すんの!?
Idiot! First they gotta get engaged!
(カズ)バカ！ その前に
ゆいのーってのがあるべ！
- What's that?
- Congrats!
(オサム)何それ！
(児童)おめでとう！
Hey!
おーい！ 朝の会 始めるぞ｡
I'm ready to get started.
HOPE
Hinazuki is due to be murdered tomorrow.
《雛月が殺されるのは あした》
March 1st.
《３月１日…
ここからが本当の勝負》
This is the real showdown.
See you, Hiromi!
したっけ！ ヒロミ！
(ヒロミ)また あしたね！
See you tomorrow!
Hey, Hinazuki...
ねえ雛月｡ あした迎えに行くから
一緒に登校しようよ｡ (雛月)いいよ｡
I'll pick you up at your house tomorrow.
Let's walk to school together.
Okay.
あっ お母さん…｡
Mom...
Good evening.
こんばんは｡
Well, I'll stop by tomorrow morning!
じゃ あした朝 迎えに来るね｡
(目覚まし時計の音)
See you later!
いってきまーす｡
はーい｡
Okay!
I left the house a little early.
＜少し早めに家を出た＞
March 1st, 1988.
＜昭和63年 ３月１日＞
The day Hinazuki
disappeared 18 years ago.
＜18年前 雛月がいなくなった日＞
(チャイム)
おはようございます｡
Good morning.
But today is different.
＜けど 今日は違う＞
Good morning, Fujinuma.
おはよう 藤沼｡
Good morning.
おはよう｡
Hinazuki isn't going anywhere.
＜雛月は いなくならない＞
Well, see you later.
それじゃあ いってきます｡
- Morning!
Circumstances have changed a lot
between 18 years ago and now.
＜18年前と今回とでは 状況が
ずいぶん変わってきている＞
Satoru's got guts!
わあ 悟君 大胆！
Hinazuki was targeted
雛月が狙われたのはいつも公園で
独りぼっちだったのが原因だ
because she was
always alone in the park.
Well, you guys all
better be there tomorrow.
じゃあ みんな
あした休まないでよ！
- Sure!
- Of course.
おう！
(ケンヤ･ヒロミ)当然｡ うん｡
Yep.
Those circumstances
disappeared days ago.
＜数日前から
その状況は なくなっている＞
Hey, let's stop at the children's center.
ねえ 児童館 寄ろうよ｡
(雛月)え？
And I'm with her today.
＜しかも 今日は
俺がついている＞
I want to get home early today.
今日は 早く帰りたいんだけど｡
Don't be like that. Hang out with me.
そんなこと言わないで
付き合ってよ｡
Okay.
うん｡
《大丈夫だ》
It'll be fine.
I win again.
(雛月)また 私の勝ち｡
You're good!
強っ！
《大丈夫じゃねえ！》
It's still fine!
Hey, Fujinuma...
ねえ 藤沼｡ もう帰りたい｡
I wanna go home.
Yeah.
うん｡ そうだね｡
Okay.
Snow...
(雛月)雪｡
RESTAURANT ROW
Answer the questions below:
Question 1: Make a sentence using the word "pole" in it.
The polar bear from the North Pole ate the teacher.
Answer the questions below:
Question 1: Make a sentence using the word "pole" in it.
I'll pick you up tomorrow, too!
あしたも迎えに来るから！
また あしたね！
See you then!
Okay.
うん｡
I said it as loud as I could.
＜できるだけ 大きな声を掛けた＞
It was for Hinazuki,
＜雛月に…＞
her mother inside,
＜中にいる雛月の母親に…＞
and anyone else who may
have been listening nearby.
＜近くで聞いているかもしれない
誰かに…＞
I was saying that I'm here.
＜｢俺が ここにいるぞ｣と＞
X-day is almost over.
《Ｘデーの日が終わる》
I got through it this easily?
《こんなに あっけなく？》
I'm an idiot.
《バカだな 俺も…》
Coming here...
《こんなとこ来たって…》
I did it!
《やった！》
With this one day,
I definitely changed history.
《今日の一日
間違いなく 歴史を変えたぞ！》
ふぁー…｡
≪お母さん おはよう｡
Morning, Mom.
えっ？ まだ６時前だよ？
It's not even six yet!
See you later!
What about breakfast?
いってきまーす｡
ご飯は？
After that, I couldn't sleep a wink.
＜あの後 結局
一睡もできなかった＞
And at that moment, I wanted to see
Hinazuki's face as soon as possible!
＜今は １秒でも早く
雛月の顔が見たかった＞
Morning, Hinazuki.
おはよう 雛月｡
Are you stupid?
バカなの？
(チャイム)
Is everyone still okay for today?
みんな 予定は大丈夫？
You know it!
当ったり前だべ！
We're gonna go to your
house and par-tay!
(オサム)今から 悟んち行って大騒ぎしてやる！
Then let's all go shopping first—
じゃあ ちょっと みんなで買い物…｡
Hey, Satoru! Kayo!
≪(手をたたく音)
≪(八代)おい 悟！ 加代！
Come here. I want your help.
ちょっと来て 手伝ってくれ｡
えーっ!? 何で 今日にかぎって…｡
Why today of all days?
We don't have a choice.
(雛月)仕方ないっしょ｡➡
It's probably because we blew off
the last cleaning duty.
こないだ 日直のとき
ポカやったからじゃない？
I guess...
かな…｡ 重いな…｡
This is heavy.
But no one's waiting for us.
でも 誰も待ってないって
ちょっと薄情じゃねえかな…｡
That's kind of cold-hearted.
SAKAI SUPERMARKET
BARGAIN SALE
That's exactly 5,000 yen.
(店員)
ちょうど5,000円になります｡
Okay.
はい｡
Come to think of it, it was 5,000 yen
on the nose 18 years ago, too.
《そういや 18年前も
ぴったり5,000円だったな》
I was in such high spirits
because of my birthday
《誕生日に浮かれていた俺は
持ってた金 全部使っちまって…》
that I spent all the money I had.
Did Mom and I make tons of sandwiches,
but just the two of us ate them?
《おふくろと２人で
大量のサンドイッチを作って 食べたんだっけ
I'm back!
ただいま｡
(雛月･悟)わっ！
One, two...
(オサム)ヘヘ せーの…｡
SATORU & HINAZUKI
HAPPY BIRTHDAY!!
Satoru! Hinazuki!
(４人)悟！ 雛月！
誕生日おめでとう！
Happy birthday!
Y-You secretly made all this?
な… 内緒で作ってたの!?
They said they wanted to do it
themselves, so I gave them a hand.
(佐知子)みんなが自分たちでやりたいって言うから
協力したさ｡
Don't tell me...
あっ まさか 放課後の手伝いも…｡
the after school duty, too...
Yep. We asked Mr. Yashiro.
うん｡ 八代先生に頼んだ｡
He told us it was Hinazuki's birthday, too.
雛月の誕生日も教えてくれたよ｡➡
Happy Birthday
Satoru
Kayo
Well, we did want to surprise you a bit.
まっ
ちょっと驚かしたかったんだ｡
I was surprised!
驚いたよ！
And Satoru insisted on getting two cakes.
ケーキはさ
悟が どうしても２つ欲しいっていうから｡
I'm sorry, Fujinuma.
ごめん 藤沼｡
I didn't have time to finish your present.
私 プレゼント
間に合わなかった…｡
Were you working on something?
もしかして 何か作ってくれてた？
うん｡
Yeah...
I see.
《そっか｡
俺から離れたがってたのって…》
She wanted to go home early for that.
I almost had it done last night,
but I fell asleep.
昨日 もう少しだったのに
寝ちゃった｡
Don't worry about it.
気にすんなよ｡
後で ちょうだい｡
Give it to me later.
All right, everyone!
じゃあさ みんな！ 5,000円分の材料で
サンドイッチ作ろうぜ！
Let's make sandwiches
with 5,000 yen worth of ingredients!
Yeah!
You used all the money?!
あのお金 全部使ったの!?
It was a lot of fun
making sandwiches together.
＜大勢でやる サンドイッチ作りは
とても楽しかった＞
Unlike 18 years ago,
＜18年前と違って
１日で 全部 食べきった＞
we finished them all off in one day.
It's fun having friends.
＜友達がいるって楽しいな＞
Hinazuki and I got
several presents from everyone.
＜俺と雛月は みんなから
たくさんのﾌﾟﾚｾﾞﾝﾄをもらった＞
And then...
＜そして…＞
Open it!
開けてみてよ｡
Thank you, Fujinuma.
ありがとう 藤沼｡
Everyone, thank you.
みんなも ありがとう｡
We'll clean up here.
(ケンヤ)
俺たち 片付けておくからさ｡
Walk Hinazuki home.
(カズ)雛月 送ってこいよ｡
I-It's cold...
さっ… 寒い！
バカなの？
Are you stupid?
W-Well, see you.
じゃ… じゃあな｡
Here.
(雛月)ほら｡➡
You...
藤沼と… みんなも友達になれて
よかった｡➡
and the others, too...
I'm glad we became friends.
Thank you for today.
今日は ありがとう｡
I'll give you your present tomorrow.
プレゼント あした渡すね｡
約束｡
That's a promise.
Okay. I can't wait.
うん！ 約束！
Good night.
おやすみ｡
I did it!
《やった… やったぞ！》
I won!
《乗り切った！》
I changed history!
《俺は 歴史を変えたんだ！》
When I got home,
everyone had already gone.
＜家に帰ると もう
みんなは いなかった＞
My exhaustion from the day before
had reached its peak
昨日からの疲れがピークに達し
and my tense feelings
relaxed all at once.
張り詰めていた気持ちが
一気に緩んで➡
I collapsed then and there
and slept like a log.
そのまま倒れ
泥のように眠ってしまった＞
MIKOTO ELEMENTARY SCHOOL
Crap! I'm late!
《ヤッベえ！ 遅刻だ！》
Good morning!
おはようございます！
Satoru.
おっ 悟｡
遅刻 取り消しっと｡
I was about to mark you as tardy.
S-Safe...
《セ… セーフ》
Is Kayo the only one who's late?
(八代)遅刻は 加代一人だけか｡
Hinazuki didn't come
to school the next day.
＜翌日 雛月は
学校に来なかった＞
The last promise made between me
and Hinazuki was never fulfilled.
＜雛月と最後に交わした約束は
果たされなかった＞